I am a visionary.
Illuminating galaxies to witness the birth of stars.
Sharpening our understanding of extreme weather events.
I am a helper.
Guiding the blind through a crowded world.
I was thinking about running to the store.
And giving voice to those who cannot speak.
To not make me laugh.
I am a transformer.
Harnessing gravity to store renewable power.
And paving the way towards unlimited clean energy for us all.
I am a trainer.
Teaching robots to assist.
To watch out for danger.
And help save lives.
I am a healer.
Providing a new generation of cures.
And new levels of patient care.
Doctor, that I am allergic to penicillin.
Is it still okay to take the medications?
Definitely.
These antibiotics don't contain penicillin.
So it's perfectly safe for you to take them.
I am a navigator.
Generating virtual scenarios.
To let us safely explore the real world.
And understand every decision.
I even helped write the script.
Breathe life into the words.
En muchos idiomas.
Y escribí la música.
I am AI.
Brought to life by NVIDIA.
Deep learning.
And brilliant minds.
Everywhere.
Please welcome to the stage NVIDIA founder and CEO Jensen Wong.
Welcome to GTC.
I hope you realize this is not a concert.
You have arrived at a developer's conference.
There will be a lot of science described.
Algorithms.
Computer architecture.
Mathematics.
I sensed a very heavy weight in the room all of a sudden.
Almost like you were in the wrong place.
No conference in the world is there a greater assembly of researchers from such diverse fields of science.
From climate tech to radio sciences trying to figure out how to use AI to robotically control MIMOs for next generation 6G radios.
Robotic self-driving cars.
Even artificial intelligence.
First I noticed a sense of relief there all of a sudden.
Also this conference is represented by some amazing companies.
This list, this is not the attendees.
These are the presenters.
And what's amazing is this.
If you take away all of my friends, close friends, Michael Dell is sitting right there.
In the IT industry.
All of the friends I grew up with in the industry.
If you take away that list, this is what's amazing.
These are the presenters of the non-IT industries using accelerated computing to solve problems that normal computers can't.
It's represented in life sciences, healthcare, genomics, transportation of course, retail, logistics, manufacturing, industrial.
The gamut of industries represented is truly amazing.
And you're not here to attend, only you're here to present.
To talk about your research.
$100 trillion of the world's industries is represented in this room today.
This is absolutely amazing.
There is absolutely something happening.
There is something going on.
The industry is being transformed, not just ours.
Because the computer industry, the computer is the single most important instrument of society today.
Fundamental transformations in computing affects every industry.
But how did we start?
How did we get here?
I made a little cartoon for you.
Literally I drew this.
In one page, this is Nvidia's journey.
Started in 1993.
This might be the rest of the talk.
1993.
This is our journey.
We were founded in 1993.
There are several important events that happened along the way.
I'll just highlight a few.
In 2006, CUDA, which has turned out to have been a revolutionary computing model.
We thought it was revolutionary then.
It was going to be an overnight success.
And almost 20 years later it happened.
We saw it coming.
Two decades later.
In 2012, AlexNet, AI and CUDA made first contact.
In 2016, recognizing the importance of this computing model, we invented a brand new type of computer.
We called it DGX1.
170 teraflops in this supercomputer.
8 GPUs connected together for the very first time.
I hand delivered the very first DGX1 to a startup located in San Francisco called OpenAI.
DGX1 was the world's first AI supercomputer.
Remember, 170 teraflops.
2017, the transformer arrived.
2022, chat GPT captured the world's imaginations.
Have people realize the importance and the capabilities of artificial intelligence.
In 2023, generative AI emerged.
And a new industry begins.
Why?
Why is a new industry?
Because the software never existed before.
We are now producing software.
Using computers to write software.
Producing software that never existed before.
It is a brand new category.
It took share from nothing.
It's a brand new category.
And the way you produce the software is unlike anything we've ever done before.
In data centers, generating tokens, producing floating point numbers at very large scale.
As if in the beginning of this last industrial revolution,
When people realized that you would set up factories, apply energy to it.
And this invisible valuable thing called electricity came out.
AC generators.
And 100 years later, 200 years later, we are now creating new types of electrons.
Tokens.
Using infrastructure we call factories, AI factories,
To generate this new incredibly valuable thing called artificial intelligence.
A new industry has emerged.
Well, we're going to talk about many things about this new industry.
We're going to talk about how we're going to do computing next.
We're going to talk about the type of software that you build because of this new industry.
The new software.
How you would think about this new software.
What about applications in this new industry?
And then maybe what's next?
And how can we start preparing today for what is about to come next?
Well, but before I start, I want to show you the soul of NVIDIA.
The soul of our company.
At the intersection of computer graphics, physics, and artificial intelligence,
all intersecting inside a computer, in Omniverse, in a virtual world simulation.
Everything we're going to show you today, literally everything we're going to show you today,
is a simulation, not animation.
It's only beautiful because it's physics.
The world is beautiful.
It's only amazing because it's being animated with robotics.
It's being animated with artificial intelligence.
What you're about to see all day is completely generated, completely simulated in Omniverse.
And all of it, what you're about to enjoy is the world's first concert where everything is homemade.
Everything is homemade.
You're about to watch some home videos.
So sit back and enjoy yourself.
The World of NVIDIA
God, I love NVIDIA.
Accelerated computing has reached the tipping point.
General purpose computing has run out of steam.
We need another way of doing computing so that we can continue to scale,
so that we can continue to drive down the cost of computing,
so that we can continue to consume more and more computing while being sustainable.
Accelerated computing is a dramatic speed up over general purpose computing.
And in every single industry we engage, and I'll show you many,
the impact is dramatic.
But in no industry is it more important than our own.
The industry of using simulation tools to create products.
In this industry, it is not about driving down the cost of computing,
it's about driving up the scale of computing.
We would like to be able to simulate the entire product that we do,
completely in full fidelity, completely digitally,
and essentially what we call digital twins.
We would like to design it, build it, simulate it, operate it, completely digitally.
In order to do that, we need to accelerate an entire industry.
And today, I would like to announce that we have some partners who are joining us in this journey
to accelerate their entire ecosystem,
so that we can bring the world into accelerated computing.
But there's a bonus.
When you become accelerated, your infrastructure is Cuda GPUs.
And when that happens, it's exactly the same infrastructure for generative AI.
And so I'm just delighted to announce several very important partnerships.
There are some of the most important companies in the world.
Ansys does engineering simulation for what the world makes.
We're partnering with them to Cuda accelerate the Ansys ecosystem,
to connect Ansys to the omniverse digital twin.
Incredible.
The thing that's really great is that the install base of video GPU accelerated systems are all over the world,
in every cloud, in every system, all over enterprises.
And so the applications they accelerate will have a giant install base to go serve.
End users will have amazing applications.
And of course, system makers and CSPs will have great customer demand.
Synopsys.
Synopsys is NVIDIA's literally first software partner.
They were there on the very first day of our company.
Synopsys revolutionized the chip industry with high-level design.
We are going to Cuda accelerate Synopsys.
We're accelerating computational lithography, one of the most important applications that nobody's ever known about.
In order to make chips, we have to push lithography to a limit.
NVIDIA has created a library, a domain-specific library, that accelerates computational lithography.
Incredibly.
Once we can accelerate and software-define all of TSMC, who is announcing today that they're going to go into production with NVIDIA CULIFO,
once the software defined and accelerated, the next step is to apply generative AI to the future of semiconductor manufacturing, pushing geometry even further.
Cadence builds the world's essential EDA and SDA tools.
We also use cadence.
Between these three companies, Ansys, Synopsys and Cadence, we basically build NVIDIA.
Together, we are Cuda accelerating Cadence.
They're also building a supercomputer out of NVIDIA GPUs so that their customers could do fluid dynamic simulation at a hundred, a thousand times scale.
Basically, a wind tunnel in real time.
Cadence Millennium, a supercomputer with NVIDIA GPUs inside.
A software company building supercomputers.
I love seeing that.
Building Cadence co-pilots together.
Imagine a day when Cadence, Synopsys, Ansys tool providers would offer you AI co-pilots so that we have thousands and thousands of co-pilot assistants helping us design chips, design systems.
And we're also going to connect Cadence Digital Twin Platform to Omniverse.
As you can see the trend here, we're accelerating the world's CAE, EDA and SDA so that we could create our future in digital twins.
And we're going to connect them all to Omniverse, the fundamental operating system for future digital twins.
One of the industries that benefited tremendously from scale, and you know, you all know this one very well, large language models.
Basically, after the transformer was invented, we were able to scale large language models at incredible rates, effectively doubling every six months.
Now, how is it possible that by doubling every six months that we have grown the industry, we have grown the computational requirements so far?
And the reason for that is quite simply this.
If you double the size of the model, you double the size of your brain, you need twice as much information to go fill it.
And so every time you double your parameter count, you also have to appropriately increase your training token count.
The combination of those two numbers becomes the computation scale you have to support.
The latest, the state-of-the-art OpenAI model is approximately 1.8 trillion parameters.
1.8 trillion parameters required several trillion tokens to go train.
So a few trillion parameters on the order of a few trillion tokens on the order of when you multiply the two of them together,
approximately 30, 40, 50 billion quadrillion floating point operations per second.
Now, we just have to do some CO math right now.
Just hang with me.
So you have 30 billion quadrillion.
A quadrillion is like a PETA.
And so if you had a PETA flop GPU, you would need 30 billion seconds to go compute, to go train that model.
30 billion seconds is approximately 1,000 years.
Well, 1,000 years, it's worth it.
I'd like to do it sooner, but it's worth it.
Which is usually my answer when most people tell me, hey, how long is it going to take to do something?
So we've got 20 years. It's worth it.
But can we do it next week?
And so 1,000 years, 1,000 years.
So what we need, what we need are bigger GPUs.
We need much, much bigger GPUs.
We recognized this early on, and we realized that the answer is to put a whole bunch of GPUs together.
And, of course, innovate a whole bunch of things along the way, like inventing tensor cores,
advancing MV links so that we could create essentially virtually giant GPUs,
and connecting them all together with amazing networks from a company called Mellanox,
InfiniBand, so that we could create these giant systems.
And so DGX1 was our first version, but it wasn't the last.
We built supercomputers all the way, all along the way.
In 2021, we had Selene, 4,500 GPUs or so.
And then in 2023, we built one of the largest AI supercomputers in the world.
It's just come online, EOS.
And as we're building these things, we're trying to help the world build these things.
And in order to help the world build these things, we got to build them first.
We build the chips, the systems, the networking, all of the software necessary to do this.
You should see these systems.
Imagine writing a piece of software that runs across the entire system,
distributing the computation across thousands of GPUs,
but inside are thousands of smaller GPUs, millions of GPUs to distribute work across all of that
and to balance the workload so that you can get the most energy efficiency,
the best computation time, keep your costs down.
And so those fundamental innovations is what got us here.
And here we are as we see the miracle of CHAT GPT emerge in front of us.
We also realize we have a long ways to go.
We need even larger models.
We're going to train it with multimodality data, not just text on the Internet,
but we're going to train it on text and images and graphs and charts.
And just as we learn, watching TV.
And so there's going to be a whole bunch of watching video so that these models can be grounded in physics,
understands that an arm doesn't go through a wall.
And so these models would have common sense by watching a lot of the world's video
combined with a lot of the world's languages.
It'll use things like synthetic data generation, just as you and I do.
When we try to learn, we might use our imagination to simulate how it's going to end up,
just as I did when I was preparing for this keynote.
I was simulating it all along the way.
I hope it's going to turn out as well as I had it in my head.
As I was simulating how this keynote was going to turn out,
somebody did say that another performer did her performance completely on a treadmill
so that she could be in shape to deliver it with full energy.
I didn't do that.
If I get a little wind in about 10 minutes into this, you know what happens.
And so where were we?
We're sitting here using synthetic data generation.
We're going to use reinforcement learning.
We're going to practice it in our mind.
We're going to have AI working with AI training each other, just like student, teacher, debaters.
All of that is going to increase the size of our model.
It's going to increase the amount of data that we have,
and we're going to have to build even bigger GPUs.
Hopper is fantastic, but we need bigger GPUs.
And so, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to introduce you to a very, very big GPU.
Named after David Blackwell, mathematician, game theorist, probability.
We thought it was a perfect name.
Blackwell, ladies and gentlemen, enjoy this.
Thank you.
Blackwell is not a chip.
Blackwell is the name of a platform.
People think we make GPUs, and we do, but GPUs don't look the way they used to.
Here's, if you will, the heart of the Blackwell system,
and this inside the company is not called Blackwell, it's just a number.
And this, this is Blackwell sitting next to, oh, this is the most advanced GPU in the world in production today.
This is Hopper.
Hopper changed the world.
This is Blackwell.
It's okay, Hopper.
You're very good.
Good boy.
Well, good girl.
208 billion transistors, and so you could see, I can see, there's a small line between two dyes.
This is the first time two dyes have abutted like this together in such a way that the two dyes think it's one chip.
There's 10 terabytes of data between it, 10 terabytes per second,
so that these two sides of the Blackwell chip have no clue which side they're on.
There's no memory locality issues, no cache issues.
It's just one giant chip.
And so when we were told that Blackwell's ambitions were beyond the limits of physics, the engineers said, so what?
And so this is what happened.
And so this is the Blackwell chip, and it goes into two types of systems.
The first one is form-fit function compatible to Hopper.
And so you slide on Hopper, and you push in Blackwell.
That's the reason why one of the challenges of ramping is going to be so efficient.
There are installations of Hoppers all over the world, and they could be the same infrastructure, same design.
The power, the electricity, the thermals, the software, identical, push it right back.
And so this is a Hopper version for the current HGX configuration.
And this is what the second Hopper looks like this.
Now, this is a prototype board.
And Janine, could I just borrow?
Ladies and gentlemen, Janine Paul.
And so this is a fully functioning board.
And I'll just be careful here.
This right here is, I don't know, $10 billion?
The second one's five.
It gets cheaper after that, so any customers in the audience, it's OK.
All right, but this one's quite expensive.
This is the bring-up board.
And the way it's going to go to production is like this one here.
And so you're going to take this.
It has two Blackwell chips and four Blackwell dies connected to a Grace CPU.
The Grace CPU has a super-fast chip-to-chip link.
What's amazing is this computer is the first of its kind where this much computation, first of all, fits into this small of a place.
Second, it's memory coherent.
They feel like they're just one big happy family working on one application together.
And so everything is coherent within it.
Just the amount of, you know, you saw the numbers.
There's a lot of terabytes this and terabytes that.
But this is a miracle.
This is this.
Let's see, what are some of the things on here?
There's an MV link on top, PCI Express on the bottom, on your, which one is mine, and your left.
One of them, it doesn't matter.
One of them is a CPU chip-to-chip link.
It's my left or your, depending on which side.
I was trying to sort that out and I just kind of, it doesn't matter.
Hopefully it comes plugged in, so.
Okay, so this is the Grace Blackwell system.
But there's more.
So it turns out, it turns out all of the specs is fantastic, but we need a whole lot of new features.
In order to push the limits beyond, if you will, the limits of physics.
We would like to always get a lot more X-factors.
And so one of the things that we did was we invented another transformer engine.
Another transformer engine, the second generation.
It has the ability to dynamically and automatically rescale and recast numerical formats to a lower precision whenever it can.
Remember, artificial intelligence is about probability.
And so you kind of have, you know, 1.7, approximately 1.7 times approximately 1.4 to be approximately something else.
Does that make sense?
And so the ability for the mathematics to retain the precision and the range necessary in that particular stage of the pipeline, super important.
And so this is, it's not just about the fact that we designed a smaller ALU.
The world's not quite that simple.
You've got to figure out when you can use that across a computation that is thousands of GPUs.
It's running for weeks and weeks and weeks, and you want to make sure that the training job is going to converge.
And so this new transformer engine, we have a fifth generation NVLink.
It's now twice as fast as Hopper, but very importantly, it has computation in the network.
And the reason for that is because when you have so many different GPUs working together, we have to share our information with each other.
We have to synchronize and update each other.
And every so often, we have to reduce the partial products and then rebroadcast out the partial products, the sum of the partial products back to everybody else.
And so there's a lot of what is called all reduce and all to all and all gather.
It's all part of this area of synchronization and collectives so that we can have GPUs working with each other.
Having extraordinarily fast links and being able to do mathematics right in the network allows us to essentially amplify even further.
So even though it's one point eight terabytes per second, it's effectively higher than that.
And so it's many times that of Hopper.
The likelihood of a supercomputer running for weeks on end is approximately zero.
And the reason for that is because there's so many components working at the same time.
The statistic, the probability of them working continuously is very low.
And so we need to make sure that whenever there is a well, we checkpoint and restart as often as we can.
But if we have the ability to detect a weak chip or a weak note early, we can retire it and maybe swap in another processor.
That ability to keep the utilization of the supercomputer high, especially when you just spent two billion dollars building it, is super important.
And so we put in a RAS engine, a reliability engine that does a hundred percent self-test in system test of every single gate,
every single bit of memory on the Blackwell chip and all the memory that's connected to it.
It's almost as if we shipped with every single chip its own advanced tester that we test our chips with.
This is the first time we're doing this. Super excited about it.
Secure AI.
Only this conference do they clap for RAS.
The secure AI.
Obviously, you've just spent hundreds of millions of dollars creating a very important AI.
And the code, the intelligence of that AI is encoded into parameters.
You want to make sure that on the one hand, you don't lose it. On the other hand, it doesn't get contaminated.
And so we now have the ability to encrypt data, of course, at rest, but also in transit and while it's being computed.
It's all encrypted. And so we now have the ability to encrypt and transmission.
And when we're computing it, it is in a trusted, trusted environment, trusted engine environment.
And the last thing is decompression.
Moving data in and out of these nodes when the compute is so fast becomes really essential.
And so we've put in a high line speed compression engine and effectively moves data 20 times faster in and out of these computers.
These computers are so powerful and there's such a large investment, the last thing we want to do is have them be idle.
And so all of these capabilities are intended to keep Blackwell fed and as busy as possible.
Overall, compared to Hopper, it is two and a half times, two and a half times the FP8 performance for training per chip.
It also has this new format called FP6 so that even though the computation speed is the same,
the bandwidth that's amplified because of the memory, the amount of parameters you can store in the memory is now amplified.
FP4 effectively doubles the throughput. This is vitally important for inference.
One of the things that is becoming very clear is that whenever you use a computer with AI on the other side,
when you're chatting with the chatbot, when you're asking it to review or make an image,
remember in the back is a GPU generating tokens.
Some people call it inference, but it's more appropriately generation.
The way that computing has done in the past was retrieval.
You would grab your phone, you would touch something, some signals go off, basically an email goes off to some storage somewhere.
There's pre-recorded content, somebody wrote a story or somebody made an image or somebody recorded a video.
That record pre-recorded content is then streamed back to the phone and recomposed in a way based on a recommender system to present the information to you.
You know that in the future, the vast majority of that content will not be retrieved.
And the reason for that is because that was pre-recorded by somebody who doesn't understand the context,
which is the reason why we have to retrieve so much content.
If you can be working with an AI that understands the context, who you are, for what reason you're fetching this information,
and produces the information for you just the way you like it,
the amount of energy we save, the amount of networking bandwidth we save, the amount of waste of time we save will be tremendous.
The future is generative, which is the reason why we call it generative AI, which is the reason why this is a brand new industry.
The way we compute is fundamentally different.
We created a processor for the generative AI era.
And one of the most important parts of it is content token generation.
We call it, this format is FP4.
Well, that's a lot of computation.
5X, the token generation, 5X, the inference capability of Hopper seems like enough.
But why stop there?
The answer is it's not enough.
And I'm going to show you why.
I'm going to show you why.
And so we would like to have a bigger GPU, even bigger than this one.
And so we decided to scale it.
And notice, but first, let me just tell you how we've scaled.
Over the course of the last eight years, we've increased computation by 1,000 times, eight years, 1,000 times.
Remember, back in the good old days of Moore's Law, it was 2X, well, 5X every, what, 10X every five years.
That's easiest math.
10X every five years, 100 times every 10 years, 100 times every 10 years.
In the middle of the heydays of the PC revolution, 100 times every 10 years.
In the last eight years, we've gone 1,000 times.
We have two more years to go.
And so that puts it in perspective.
The rate at which we're advancing computing is insane.
And it's still not fast enough, so we built another chip.
This chip is just an incredible chip.
We call it the NVLink switch.
It's 50 billion transistors.
It's almost the size of Hopper all by itself.
This switch chip has four NVLinks in it, each 1.8 terabytes per second.
And it has computation in it, as I mentioned.
What is this chip for?
If we were to build such a chip, we can have every single GPU talk to every other GPU at full speed at the same time.
That's insane.
It doesn't even make sense.
But if you could do that, if you can find a way to do that and build a system to do that that's cost-effective,
how incredible would it be that we could have all these GPUs connect over a coherent link so that they effectively are one giant GPU?
Well, one of the great inventions in order to make it cost-effective is that this chip has to drive copper directly.
The surities of this chip is just a phenomenal invention so that we could do direct drive to copper.
And as a result, you can build a system that looks like this.
Now, this system is kind of insane.
This is one DGX.
This is what a DGX looks like now.
Remember, just six years ago, it was pretty heavy, but I was able to lift it.
I delivered the first DGX1 to OpenAI, and the researchers there, the pictures are on the internet, and we all autographed it.
And if you come to my office, it's autographed there.
It's really beautiful.
But you can lift it.
This DGX, this DGX, that DGX, by the way, was 170 teraflops.
If you're not familiar with the numbering system, that's 0.17 petaflops.
So this is 720.
The first one I delivered to OpenAI was 0.17.
You can round it up to 0.2. It won't make any difference.
But by then, it was like, wow, you know, 30 more teraflops.
And so this is now 720 petaflops, almost an exaflop for training, and the world's first one exaflops machine in one rack.
Just so you know, there are only a couple, two, three exaflops machines on the planet as we speak.
And so this is an exaflops AI system in one single rack.
Well, let's take a look at the back of it.
So this is what makes it possible.
That's the back, that's the back, the DGX MV link spine.
130 terabytes per second goes to the back of that chassis.
That is more than the aggregate bandwidth of the internet.
So we could basically send everything to everybody within a second.
And so we have 5,000 cables, 5,000 MV link cables in total two miles.
Now, this is the amazing thing. If we had to use optics, we would have had to use transceivers and retimers.
And those transceivers and retimers alone would have cost 20,000 watts, two kilowatts of just transceivers alone, just to drive the MV link spine.
As a result, we did it completely for free over MV link switch, and we were able to save the 20 kilowatts for computation.
This entire rack is 120 kilowatts, so that 20 kilowatts makes a huge difference.
It's liquid cooled. What goes in is 25 degrees C about room temperature.
What comes out is 45 degrees C about your jacuzzi.
So room temperature goes in, jacuzzi comes out, two liters per second.
We could sell a peripheral.
600,000 parts.
Somebody used to say, you know, you guys make GPUs, and we do, but this is what a GPU looks like to me.
When somebody says GPU, I see this.
Two years ago, when I saw a GPU, it was the HGX. It was 70 pounds, 35,000 parts.
Our GPUs now are 600,000 parts and 3,000 pounds, 3,000 pounds, 3,000 pounds.
That's kind of like the weight of a, you know, carbon fiber Ferrari.
I don't know if that's a useful metric, but everybody's going, I feel it.
I feel it. I get it. I get that.
Now that you mention that, I feel it.
I don't know what's 3,000 pounds.
Okay, so 3,000 pounds, ton and a half.
So it's not quite an elephant.
So this is what a DGX looks like.
Now let's see what it looks like in operation.
Okay, let's imagine, how do we put this to work and what does that mean?
Well, if you were to train a GPT model, 1.8 trillion parameter model,
it took about, apparently about three to five months or so with 25,000 amperes.
If we were to do it with Hopper, it would probably take something like 8,000 GPUs
and it would consume 15 megawatts, 8,000 GPUs and 15 megawatts.
It would take 90 days, about three months.
And that would allow you to train something that is, you know, this groundbreaking AI model.
And this is obviously not as expensive as anybody would think, but it's 8,000 GPUs.
It's still a lot of money.
And so 8,000 GPUs, 15 megawatts.
If you were to use Blackwell to do this, it would only take 2,000 GPUs.
2,000 GPUs, same 90 days, but this is the amazing part.
Only four megawatts of power.
So from 15, that's right.
And that's our goal.
Our goal is to continuously drive down the cost and the energy.
They're directly proportional to each other.
Cost and energy associated with the computing so that we can continue to expand
and scale up the computation that we have to do to train the next generation models.
Well, this is training.
Inference or generation is vitally important going forward.
You know, probably some half of the time that NVIDIA GPUs are in the cloud these days,
it's being used for token generation.
You know, they're either doing co-pilot this or, you know, chat GPT that
or all these different models that are being used when you're interacting with it
or generating images or generating videos, generating proteins, generating chemicals.
There's a bunch of generation going on.
All of that is in the category of computing we call inference.
But inference is extremely hard for large language models
because these large language models have several properties.
One, they're very large.
And so it doesn't fit on one GPU.
This is, imagine Excel doesn't fit on one GPU, you know?
And imagine some application you're running on a daily basis doesn't fit on one computer.
Like a video game doesn't fit on one computer.
And most, in fact, do.
And many times in the past, hyper-scale computing,
many applications for many people fit on the same computer.
And now, all of a sudden, this one inference application
where you're interacting with this chatbot,
that chatbot requires a supercomputer in the back to run it.
And that's the future.
The future is generative with these chatbots,
and these chatbots are trillions of tokens, trillions of parameters,
and they have to generate tokens at interactive rates.
Now, what does that mean?
Oh, well, three tokens is about a word.
You know, the space, the final frontier, these are the adventures.
That's like 80 tokens.
Okay?
I don't know if that's useful to you.
And so, you know, the art of communications is selecting good analogies.
Yeah, this is not going well.
Everyone's like, I don't know what he's talking about.
Never seen Star Trek.
And so, here we are, we're trying to generate these tokens.
When you're interacting with it, you're hoping that the tokens come back to you
as quickly as possible and as quickly as you can read it.
And so, the ability for generation tokens is really important.
You have to paralyze the work of this model across many, many GPUs
so that you could achieve several things.
One, on the one hand, you would like throughput
because that throughput reduces the cost, the overall cost per token of generating.
So, your throughput dictates the cost of delivering the service.
On the other hand, you have another interactive rate,
which is another tokens per second, where it's about per user.
And that has everything to do with quality of service.
And so, these two things compete against each other.
And we have to find a way to distribute work across all of these different GPUs
and paralyze it in a way that allows us to achieve both.
And it turns out the search space is enormous.
You know, I told you there's going to be math involved.
And everybody's going, oh, dear.
I heard some gasps just now when I put up that slide.
So, this right here, the y-axis is tokens per second, data center throughput.
The x-axis is tokens per second, interactivity of the person.
And notice the upper right is the best.
You want interactivity to be very high, number of tokens per second per user.
You want the tokens per second per data center to be very high.
The upper right is terrific.
However, it's very hard to do that.
And in order for us to search for the best answer across every single one of those intersections,
x, y coordinates, in case you just look at every single x, y coordinate,
all those blue dots came from some repartitioning of the software.
Some optimizing solution has to go and figure out whether to use tensor parallel, expert parallel,
pipeline parallel, or data parallel, and distribute this enormous model across all these different GPUs
and sustain the performance that you need.
This exploration space would be impossible if not for the programmability of NVIDIA's GPUs.
And so we could, because of CUDA, because we have such a rich ecosystem,
we could explore this universe and find that green roof line.
It turns out that green roof line, notice you got TP2EPADP4,
it means two tensor parallel, tensor parallel across two GPUs, expert parallel across eight, data parallel across four.
Notice on the other end, you got tensor parallel across four and expert parallel across 16.
The configuration, the distribution of that software, it's a different, different runtime
that would produce these different results.
And you have to go discover that roof line.
Well, that's just one model.
And this is just one configuration of a computer.
Imagine all of the models being created around the world
and all the different configurations of systems that are going to be available.
So now that you understand the basics,
let's take a look at inference of Blackwell compared to Hopper.
And this is the extraordinary thing.
In one generation, because we created a system that's designed for trillion parameter generative AI,
the inference capability of Blackwell is off the charts.
And in fact, it is some 30 times Hopper.
Yeah.
For large language models, for large language models like ChatGPT and others like it,
the blue line is Hopper.
I gave you, imagine we didn't change the architecture of Hopper.
We just made it a bigger chip.
We just used the latest, you know, greatest 10 terabytes, you know, terabytes per second.
We connected the two chips together.
We got this giant 208 billion parameter chip.
How would we have performed if nothing else changed?
And it turns out quite wonderfully, quite wonderfully.
And that's the purple line, but not as great as it could be.
And that's where the FP4 Tensor Core, the new transformer engine,
and very importantly, the NVLink switch.
And the reason for that is because all these GPUs have to share the results, partial products.
Whenever they do all to all, all gather, whenever they communicate with each other,
that NVLink switch is communicating almost 10 times faster
than what we could do in the past using the fastest networks.
Okay, so Blackwell is going to be just an amazing system for generative AI.
And in the future, in the future, data centers are going to be thought of,
as I mentioned earlier, as an AI factory.
An AI factory's goal in life is to generate revenues, generate, in this case,
intelligence in this facility, not generating electricity, as in AC generators,
but of the last industrial revolution and this industrial revolution, the generation of intelligence.
And so this ability is super, super important.
The excitement of Blackwell is really off the charts.
You know, when we first, when we first, you know, this is a year and a half ago,
two years ago, I guess two years ago, when we first started to go to market with Hopper,
you know, we had the benefit of two CSPs joined us in a lunch.
And we were, you know, delighted.
And so we had two customers.
So we have more now.
Unbelievable excitement for Blackwell, unbelievable excitement.
And there's a whole bunch of different configurations.
Of course, I showed you the configurations that slide into the Hopper form factor,
so that it's easy to upgrade.
I showed you examples that are liquid cooled, that are the extreme versions of it,
one entire rack that's connected by NVLink 72.
We're going to, Blackwell is going to be ramping to the world's AI companies,
of which there are so many now, doing amazing work in different modalities.
The CSPs, every CSP is geared up.
All the OEMs and ODMs, regional clouds, sovereign AIs, and telcos all over the world
are signing up to launch with Blackwell.
Blackwell would be the most successful product launch in our history.
And so I can't wait to see that.
I want to thank some partners that are joining us in this.
AWS is gearing up for Blackwell.
They're going to build the first GPU with secure AI.
They're building out a 222 exaflops system.
You know, just now when we animated, just now the digital twin,
if you saw all of those clusters coming down.
By the way, that is not just art.
That is a digital twin of what we're building.
That's how big it's going to be.
Besides infrastructure, we're doing a lot of things together with AWS.
We're CUDA accelerating SageMaker AI.
We're CUDA accelerating Bedrock AI.
Amazon Robotics is working with us using NVIDIA Omniverse and Isaac Sim.
AWS Health has NVIDIA Health integrated into it.
So AWS has really leaned into accelerated computing.
Google is gearing up for Blackwell.
GCP already has A100s, H100s, T4s, L4s, a whole fleet of NVIDIA CUDA GPUs.
And they recently announced the Gemma model that runs across all of it.
We're working to optimize and accelerate every aspect of GCP.
We're accelerating Dataproc for data processing, their data processing engine,
Jax, XLA, Vertex AI, and Mujoco for robotics.
So we're working with Google and GCP across a whole bunch of initiatives.
Oracle is gearing up for Blackwell.
Oracle is a great partner of ours for NVIDIA DGX Cloud.
And we're also working together to accelerate something that's really important
to a lot of companies, Oracle Database.
Microsoft is accelerating, and Microsoft is gearing up for Blackwell.
Microsoft and NVIDIA has a wide-ranging partnership.
We're accelerating CUDA, accelerating all kinds of services.
When you chat, obviously, and AI services that are in Microsoft Azure,
it's very, very likely NVIDIA is in the back doing the inference
and the token generation.
They built the largest NVIDIA InfiniBand supercomputer,
basically a digital twin of ours or a physical twin of ours.
We're bringing the NVIDIA ecosystem to Azure.
NVIDIA DGX Cloud to Azure.
NVIDIA Omniverse is now hosted in Azure.
NVIDIA Healthcare is in Azure.
All of it is deeply integrated and deeply connected with Microsoft Fabric.
The whole industry is gearing up for Blackwell.
This is what I'm about to show you.
Most of the scenes that you've seen so far of Blackwell
are the full fidelity design of Blackwell.
Everything in our company has a digital twin.
And, in fact, this digital twin idea is really spreading,
and it helps companies build very complicated things perfectly the first time.
And what could be more exciting than creating a digital twin
to build a computer that was built in a digital twin?
And so, let me show you what Wistron is doing.
To meet the demand for NVIDIA accelerated computing,
Wistron, one of our leading manufacturing partners,
is building digital twins of NVIDIA DGX and HGX factories
using custom software developed with Omniverse, SDKs, and APIs.
For their newest factory, Wistron started with the digital twin
to virtually integrate their multi-CAD and process simulation data into a unified view.
Testing and optimizing layouts in this physically accurate digital environment
increased worker efficiency by 51%.
During construction, the Omniverse digital twin was used to verify
that the physical build matched the digital plans.
Identifying any discrepancies early has helped avoid costly change orders.
And the results have been impressive.
Using a digital twin helped bring Wistron's factory online in half the time,
just two and a half months instead of five.
In operation, the Omniverse digital twin helps Wistron rapidly test new layouts
to accommodate new processes or improve operations in the existing space,
and monitor real-time operations using live IoT data from every machine on the production line,
which ultimately enabled Wistron to reduce end-to-end cycle times by 50% and defect rates by 40%.
With NVIDIA AI and Omniverse, NVIDIA's global ecosystem of partners
are building a new era of accelerated AI-enabled digitalization.
That's the way it's going to be in the future.
We're going to be manufacturing everything digitally first,
and then we'll manufacture it physically.
People ask me, how did it start?
What got you guys so excited?
What was it that you saw that caused you to put it all in
on this incredible idea?
And it's this.
Hang on a second.
Guys, that was going to be such a moment.
That's what happens when you don't rehearse.
This, as you know, was first contact.
2012, AlexNet.
You put a cat into this computer, and it comes out and it says, cat.
And we said, oh, my God, this is going to change everything.
You take one million numbers across three channels, RGB.
These numbers make no sense to anybody.
You put it into this software, and it compress, it dimensionally
reduces it.
It reduces it from a million dimensions, a million dimensions.
It turns it into three letters, one vector, one number.
And it's generalized.
You could have the cat be different cats.
And you could have it be the front of the cat and the back of the cat.
And you look at this thing, you say, unbelievable.
You mean any cats?
Yeah, any cat.
And it was able to recognize all these cats.
And we realized how it did it.
It systematically, structurally, it's scalable.
How big can you make it?
Well, how big do you want to make it?
And so we imagine that this is a completely new way of writing software.
And now today, as you know, you can have, you type in the word C-A-T.
And what comes out is a cat.
It went the other way.
Am I right?
Unbelievable.
How is it possible?
That's right.
How is it possible you took three letters and you generated a million pixels from it?
And it made sense.
Well, that's the miracle.
And here we are, just literally 10 years later, 10 years later, where we recognize text,
we recognize images, we recognize videos and sounds and images.
Not only do we recognize them, we understand their meaning.
We understand the meaning of the text.
That's the reason why it can chat with you.
It can summarize for you.
It understands the text.
It understood not just recognizes the English, it understood the English.
It doesn't just recognize the pixels, it understood the pixels.
And you can even condition it between two modalities.
You can have language condition image and generate all kinds of interesting things.
Well, if you can understand these things, what else can you understand that you've digitized?
The reason why we started with text and images is because we digitized those.
But what else have we digitized?
Well, it turns out we digitized a lot of things, proteins and genes and brain waves.
Anything you can digitize, so long as there's structure, we can probably learn some patterns from it.
And if we can learn the patterns from it, we can understand its meaning.
If we can understand its meaning, we might be able to generate it as well.
And so therefore, the generative AI revolution is here.
Well, what else can we generate?
What else can we learn?
Well, one of the things that we would love to learn, we would love to learn, is we would love to learn climate.
We would love to learn extreme weather.
We would love to learn how we can predict future weather at regional scales,
at sufficiently high resolution, such that we can keep people out of harm's way before harm comes.
Extreme weather cost the world $150 billion.
Surely more than that, it's not evenly distributed.
$150 billion is concentrated in some parts of the world and, of course, to some people of the world.
We need to adapt and we need to know what's coming.
And so we're creating Earth 2, a digital twin of the Earth for predicting weather.
And we've made an extraordinary invention called CoreDiv,
the ability to use generative AI to predict weather at extremely high resolution.
Let's take a look.
As the Earth's climate changes,
AI-powered weather forecasting is allowing us to more accurately predict and track severe storms,
like super typhoon Chanthu, which caused widespread damage in Taiwan and the surrounding region in 2021.
Current AI forecast models can accurately predict the track of storms,
but they are limited to 25-kilometer resolution, which can miss important details.
NVIDIA's CoreDiv is a revolutionary new generative AI model,
trained on high-resolution radar-assimilated wolf weather forecasts and AERA 5 reanalysis data.
Using CoreDiv, extreme events like Chanthu can be super resolved from 25-kilometer to 2-kilometer resolution,
with 1,000 times the speed and 3,000 times the energy efficiency of conventional weather models.
By combining the speed and accuracy of NVIDIA's weather forecasting model ForecastNet
and generative AI models like CoreDiv,
we can explore hundreds or even thousands of kilometer-scale regional weather forecasts
to provide a clear picture of the best, worst and most likely impacts of a storm.
This wealth of information can help minimize loss of life and property damage.
Today, CoreDiv is optimized for Taiwan,
but soon generative supersampling will be available as part of the NVIDIA Earth2 inference service for many regions across the globe.
The weather company has to trust the source of global weather prediction.
We are working together to accelerate their weather simulation, first principled base of simulation.
However, they're also going to integrate Earth2 CoreDiv
so that they can help businesses and countries do regional high-resolution weather prediction.
And so if you have some weather prediction you'd like to do, reach out to the weather company.
Really exciting, really exciting work.
NVIDIA Healthcare, something we started 15 years ago.
We're super, super excited about this.
This is an area where we're very, very proud.
Whether it's medical imaging or gene sequencing or computational chemistry,
it is very likely that NVIDIA is the computation behind it.
We've done so much work in this area.
Today we're announcing that we're going to do something really, really cool.
Imagine all of these AI models that are being used to generate images and audio.
But instead of images and audio, because it understood images and audio,
all the digitization that we've done for genes and proteins and amino acids,
that digitization capability is now passed through machine learning
so that we understand the language of life.
The ability to understand the language of life, of course, we saw the first evidence of it with AlphaFold.
This is really quite an extraordinary thing.
After decades of painstaking work, the world had only digitized and reconstructed
using cryo-electron microscopy or x-ray crystallography.
These different techniques painstakingly reconstructed the protein, 200,000 of them,
in just less than a year or so.
AlphaFold has reconstructed 200 million proteins,
basically every living thing that's ever been sequenced.
This is completely revolutionary.
Those models are incredibly hard for people to build,
and so what we're going to do is we're going to build them.
We're going to build them for the researchers around the world.
It won't be the only one.
There will be many other models that we create.
Let me show you what we're going to do with it.
Virtual screening for new medicines is a computationally intractable problem.
Existing techniques can only scan billions of compounds
and require days on thousands of standard compute nodes to identify new drug candidates.
NVIDIA BioNemo NIMs enable a new generative screening paradigm.
Using NIMs for protein structure prediction with AlphaFold,
molecule generation with MolMIM, and docking with DiffDock,
we can now generate and screen candidate molecules in a matter of minutes.
MolMIM can connect to custom applications to steer the generative process,
iteratively optimizing for desired properties.
These applications can be defined with BioNemo microservices or built from scratch.
Here, a physics-based simulation optimizes for a molecule's ability to bind to a target protein
while optimizing for other favorable molecular properties in parallel.
MolMIM generates high-quality drug-like molecules that bind to the target and are synthesizable,
translating to a higher probability of developing successful medicines faster.
BioNemo is enabling a new paradigm in drug discovery with NIMs,
providing on-demand microservices that can be combined to build powerful drug discovery workflows
like de novo protein design or guided molecule generation for virtual screening.
BioNemo NIMs are helping researchers and developers reinvent computational drug design.
NVIDIA MOLMIM
NVIDIA MOLMIM, MOLMIM, CoreDiff, there's a whole bunch of other models,
a whole bunch of other models, computer vision models, robotics models,
and even, of course, some really, really terrific open-source language models.
These models are groundbreaking. However, it's hard for companies to use.
How would you use it? How would you bring it into your company and integrate it into your workflow?
How would you package it up and run it?
Remember, earlier I just said that inference is an extraordinary computation problem.
How would you do the optimization for each and every one of these models
and put together the computing stack necessary to run that supercomputer
so that you can run these models in your company?
And so we have a great idea. We're going to invent a new way,
invent a new way for you to receive and operate software.
This software comes basically in a digital box. We call it a container.
And we call it the NVIDIA Inference Microservice, a NIM.
And let me explain to you what it is.
A NIM. It's a pre-trained model, so it's pretty clever.
And it is packaged and optimized to run across NVIDIA's installed base, which is very, very large.
What's inside it is incredible.
You have all these pre-trained state-of-the-art open-source models.
They could be open-source. They could be from one of our partners.
It could be created by us, like NVIDIA Moment.
It is packaged up with all of its dependencies.
So CUDA, the right version, CUDNN, the right version,
TensorFlow RT, LLM, distributing across the multiple GPUs, Triton Inference Server,
all completely packaged together.
It's optimized depending on whether you have a single GPU, multi-GPU, or multi-node of GPUs.
It's optimized for that.
And it's connected up with APIs that are simple to use.
Now, think about what an AI API is.
An AI API is an interface that you just talk to.
And so this is a piece of software in the future that has a really simple API,
and that API is called Human.
And these packages, incredible bodies of software,
will be optimized and packaged, and we'll put it on a website.
And you can download it. You can take it with you.
You can run it in any cloud. You can run it in your own data center.
You can run it in workstations if it fit.
And all you have to do is come to ai.nvidia.com.
We call it NVIDIA Inference Microservice,
but inside the company we all call it NIMS.
Okay?
Just imagine, you know, one day there's going to be one of these chatbots,
and these chatbots is going to just be in a NIM.
And you'll assemble a whole bunch of chatbots.
And that's the way software is going to be built someday.
How do we build software in the future?
It is unlikely that you'll write it from scratch
or write a whole bunch of Python code or anything like that.
It is very likely that you assemble a team of AIs.
There's probably going to be a super AI that you use
that takes the mission that you give it
and breaks it down into an execution plan.
Some of that execution plan could be handed off to another NIM.
That NIM would maybe understand SAP.
The language of SAP is ABAP.
It might understand ServiceNow
and go retrieve some information from their platforms.
It might then hand that result to another NIM
who goes off and does some calculation on it.
Maybe it's an optimization software,
a combinatorial optimization algorithm.
Maybe it's, you know, just some basic calculator.
Maybe it's Pandas to do some numerical analysis on it.
And then it comes back with its answer.
And it gets combined with everybody else's.
And because it's been presented with
this is what the right answer should look like,
it knows what right answers to produce,
and it presents it to you.
We can get a report every single day, you know, top of the hour,
that has something to do with a build plan or some forecast
or some customer alert or some bugs database
or whatever it happens to be,
and we could assemble it using all these NIMs.
And because these NIMs have been packaged up
and ready to work on your systems,
so long as you have NVIDIA GPUs in your data center or in the cloud,
these NIMs will work together as a team and do amazing things.
And so we decided, this is such a great idea,
we're going to go do that.
And so NVIDIA has NIMs running all over the company.
We have chatbots being created all over the place,
and one of the most important chatbots, of course,
is a chip designer chatbot.
You might not be surprised.
We care a lot about building chips.
And so we want to build chatbots,
AI copilots that are co-designers with our engineers.
And so this is the way we did it.
So we got ourselves a Llama 2.
This is a 70B, and it's packaged up in a NIM.
We asked it, you know, what is a CTL?
It turns out CTL is an internal program,
and it has an internal proprietary language,
but it thought the CTL was a combinatorial timing logic,
and so it describes conventional knowledge of CTL,
but that's not very useful to us.
And so we gave it a whole bunch of new examples.
This is no different than onboarding an employee.
And we say, you know, thanks for that answer.
It's completely wrong.
And then we present to them, this is what a CTL is, okay?
And so this is what a CTL is at NVIDIA.
And the CTL, as you can see, you know, CTL stands for
Compute Trace Library, which makes sense.
You know, we're tracing compute cycles all the time,
and it wrote the program.
Isn't that amazing?
And so the productivity of our chip designers can go up.
This is what you can do with a NIM.
First thing you can do with it is customize it.
We have a service called NEMO Microservice
that helps you curate the data,
preparing the data so that you can teach this onboard this AI.
You fine-tune them, and then you guardrail it.
You can even evaluate the answer,
evaluate its performance against other examples.
And so that's called the NIM.
Now, the thing that's emerging here is this.
There are three elements, three pillars of what we're doing.
The first pillar is, of course,
inventing the technology for AI models
and running AI models and packaging it up for you.
The second is to create tools to help you modify it.
First is having the AI technology.
Second is to help you modify it.
And third is infrastructure for you to fine-tune it
and evaluate it.
And then finally, the third pillar,
infrastructure for you to fine-tune it
and, if you like, deploy it.
You could deploy it on our infrastructure called DGX Cloud,
or you could deploy it on-prem.
You could deploy it anywhere you like.
Once you develop it, it's yours to take anywhere.
And so we are effectively an AI foundry.
We will do for you and the industry on AI
what TSMC does for us, building chips.
And so we go to TSMC with our big ideas.
We manufacture it, and we take it with us.
And so exactly the same thing here.
AI foundry, and the three pillars are the NIMS,
NEMO Microservice, and DGX Cloud.
The other thing that you could teach the NIMP to do
is to understand your proprietary information.
Remember, inside our company,
the vast majority of our data is not in the cloud.
It's inside our company.
It's been sitting there, you know, being used all the time,
and, gosh, it's basically NVIDIA's intelligence.
We would like to take that data, learn its meaning,
like we learned the meaning of almost anything else
that we just talked about.
Learn its meaning, and then re-index that knowledge
into a new type of database called a vector database.
And so you essentially take structured data
or unstructured data, you learn its meaning,
you encode its meaning, so now this becomes an AI database,
and that AI database, in the future, once you create it,
you can talk to it.
And so let me give you an example of what you could do.
So suppose you've got a whole bunch of multimodality data,
and one good example of that is PDF.
So you take the PDF, you take all of your PDFs,
all your favorite, you know, the stuff that is proprietary to you,
critical to your company, you can encode it.
Just as we encoded pixels of a cat,
and it becomes the word cat, we can encode all of your PDF,
and it turns into vectors that are now stored
inside your vector database.
It becomes the proprietary information of your company.
And once you have that proprietary information,
you can chat to it.
It's a smart database, so you just chat with data.
And how much more enjoyable is that?
You know, for our software team,
they just chat with the bugs database, you know?
How many bugs was there last night?
Are we making any progress?
And then after you're done talking to this bugs database,
you need therapy.
And so we have another chat bot for you.
You can do it.
Okay, so we call this Nemo Retriever,
and the reason for that is because ultimately its job
is to go retrieve information as quickly as possible.
And you just talk to it.
Hey, retrieve me this information,
and it goes, oh, it brings it back to you.
Do you mean this?
You go, yeah, perfect, okay?
And so we call it the Nemo Retriever.
Well, the Nemo service helps you create all these things,
and we have all these different NIMs.
We even have NIMs of digital humans.
I'm Rachel, your AI care manager.
Okay, so it's a really short clip,
but there were so many videos to show you,
I guess so many other demos to show you,
and so I had to cut this one short.
But this is Diana.
She is a digital human NIM,
and you just talked to her,
and she's connected, in this case,
to Hippocratic AI's large language model for healthcare,
and it's truly amazing.
She is just super smart about healthcare things, you know?
And so after Dwight, my VP of software engineering,
talks to the chat bot for Bugs Database,
then you come over here and talk to Diane.
And so Diane is completely animated with AI,
and she's a digital human.
There are so many companies that would like to build,
they're sitting on gold mines.
The enterprise IT industry is sitting on a gold mine.
It's a gold mine because they have so much understanding
of the way work is done.
They have all these amazing tools
that have been created over the years,
and they're sitting on a lot of data.
If they could take that gold mine
and turn them into co-pilots,
these co-pilots could help us do things.
And so just about every IT franchise,
IT platform in the world
that has valuable tools that people use
is sitting on a gold mine for co-pilots,
and they would like to build their own co-pilots
and their own chat bots.
And so we're announcing that NVIDIA AI Foundry
is working with some of the world's great companies.
SAP generates 87% of the world's global commerce.
Basically, the world runs on SAP.
We run on SAP.
NVIDIA and SAP are building SAP Jewel co-pilots
using NVIDIA Nemo and DGX Cloud.
ServiceNow, they run 85% of the world's Fortune 500 companies
run their people and customer service operations on ServiceNow.
And they're using NVIDIA AI Foundry
to build ServiceNow assist virtual assistants.
Cohesity backs up the world's data.
They're sitting on a gold mine of data,
hundreds of exabytes of data,
over 10,000 companies.
NVIDIA AI Foundry is working with them,
helping them build their Gaia generative AI agent.
Snowflake is a company that stores
the world's digital warehouse in the cloud
and serves over 3 billion queries a day
for 10,000 enterprise customers.
Snowflake is working with NVIDIA AI Foundry
to build co-pilots with NVIDIA Nemo and NIMS.
NetApp, nearly half of the files in the world
are stored on-prem on NetApp.
NVIDIA AI Foundry is helping them
build chatbots and co-pilots
like those vector databases and retrievers
with NVIDIA Nemo and NIMS.
And we have a great partnership with Dell.
Everybody who is building these chatbots
and generative AI,
when you're ready to run it,
you're going to need an AI factory.
And nobody is better at building end-to-end systems
of very large scale for the enterprise than Dell.
And so anybody, any company,
every company will need to build AI factories.
And it turns out that Michael is here.
He's happy to take your order.
Ladies and gentlemen, Michael Dell.
Okay, let's talk about the next wave of robotics,
the next wave of AI, robotics, physical AI.
So far, all of the AI that we've talked about
is one computer.
Data comes into one computer,
lots of the world's, if you will,
experience in digital text form.
The AI imitates us by reading a lot of the language
to predict the next words.
It's imitating you by studying all of the patterns
and all the other previous examples.
Of course, it has to understand context and so on and so forth,
but once it understands the context,
it's essentially imitating you.
We take all of the data,
we put it into a system like DGX,
we compress it into a large language model,
trillions and trillions of parameters
become billions and billions,
trillions of tokens becomes billions of parameters,
these billions of parameters becomes your AI.
Well, in order for us to go to the next wave of AI,
where the AI understands the physical world,
we're going to need three computers.
The first computer is still the same computer.
It's that AI computer that now is going to be watching video
and maybe it's doing synthetic data generation
and maybe there's a lot of human examples,
just as we have human examples in text form,
we're going to have human examples in articulation form
and the AIs will watch us, understand what is happening
and try to adapt it for themselves into the context
and because it can generalize with these foundation models,
maybe these robots can also perform in the physical world
fairly generally.
So I just described in very simple terms
essentially what just happened in large language models,
except the chat GPT moment for robotics
may be right around the corner.
And so we've been building the end-to-end systems
for robotics for some time.
I'm super, super proud of the work.
We have the AI system, DGX.
We have the lower system, which is called AGX,
for autonomous systems,
the world's first robotics processor.
When we first built this thing, people are,
what are you guys building?
It's an SOC, it's one chip,
it's designed to be very low power,
high speed sensor processing and AI.
And so if you want to run transformers in a car
or you want to run transformers in anything that moves,
we have the perfect computer for you.
It's called the Jetson.
And so the DGX on top for training the AI,
the Jetson is the autonomous processor,
and in the middle, we need another computer.
Whereas large language models have the benefit
of you providing your examples
and then doing reinforcement learning human feedback,
what is the reinforcement learning human feedback of a robot?
Well, it's reinforcement learning physical feedback.
That's how you align the robot.
That's how the robot knows that as it's learning
these articulation capabilities and manipulation capabilities,
it's going to adapt properly into the laws of physics.
And so we need a simulation engine
that represents the world digitally for the robot
so that the robot has a gym to go learn how to be a robot.
We call that virtual world Omniverse.
And the computer that runs Omniverse is called OVX.
And OVX, the computer itself, is hosted in the Azure cloud.
And so basically we built these three things, these three systems.
On top of it, we have algorithms for every single one.
Now, I'm going to show you one super example
of how AI and Omniverse are going to work together.
The example I'm going to show you is kind of insane,
but it's going to be very, very close to tomorrow.
It's a robotics building.
This robotics building is called a warehouse.
Inside the robotics building
are going to be some autonomous systems.
Some of the autonomous systems are going to be called humans,
and some of the autonomous systems are going to be called forklifts.
And these autonomous systems are going to interact with each other,
of course, autonomously,
and it's going to be overlooked upon by this warehouse
to keep everybody out of harm's way.
The warehouse is essentially an air traffic controller.
And whenever it sees something happening,
it will redirect traffic and give new waypoints,
just new waypoints to the robots and the people,
and they'll know exactly what to do.
This warehouse, this building, you can also talk to.
Of course you could talk to it.
Hey, you know, SAP Center, how are you feeling today?
For example.
And so you could ask the warehouse the same questions.
Basically, the system I just described will have Omniverse Cloud
that's hosting the virtual simulation,
and AI running on DGX Cloud,
and all of this is running in real time.
Let's take a look.
The future of heavy industries starts as a digital twin.
The AI agents helping robots, workers, and infrastructure
navigate unpredictable events in complex industrial spaces
will be built and evaluated first in sophisticated digital twins.
This Omniverse digital twin of a 100,000-square-foot warehouse
is operating as a simulation environment
that integrates digital workers,
AMRs running the NVIDIA ISAC perceptor stack,
centralized activity maps of the entire warehouse
from 100 simulated ceiling mount cameras using NVIDIA Metropolis,
and AMR route planning with NVIDIA KuOpt.
Software in-loop testing of AI agents
in this physically accurate simulated environment
enables us to evaluate and refine how the system adapts
to real-world unpredictability.
Here, an incident occurs along this AMR's planned route,
blocking its path as it moves to pick up a pallet.
NVIDIA Metropolis updates and sends a real-time occupancy map
to KuOpt where a new optimal route is calculated.
The AMR is enabled to see around corners
and improve its mission efficiency.
With generative AI-powered Metropolis vision foundation models,
operators can even ask questions using natural language.
The visual model understands nuanced activity
and can offer immediate insights to improve operations.
All of the sensor data is created in simulation
and passed to the real-time AI,
running as NVIDIA Inference Microservices, or NIMS.
And when the AI is ready to be deployed in the physical twin,
the real warehouse, we connect Metropolis and ISAC NIMS
to real sensors with the ability for continuous improvement
of both the digital twin and the AI models.
Isn't that incredible?
And so, remember,
a future facility warehouse, factory, building
will be software defined.
And so the software is running.
How else would you test the software?
So you test the software to building the warehouse,
the optimization system, in the digital twin.
What about all the robots?
All of those robots you were seeing just now,
they're all running their own autonomous robotic stack.
And so the way you integrate software in the future,
CICD in the future, for robotic systems
is with digital twins.
We've made Omniverse a lot easier to access.
We're going to create basically Omniverse cloud APIs,
four simple API in a channel,
and you can connect your application to it.
So this is going to be as wonderfully, beautifully simple
in the future that Omniverse is going to be.
And with these APIs, you're going to have
these magical digital twin capability.
We also have turned Omniverse into an AI
and integrated it with the ability to chat USD.
The language of our language is, you know, human,
and Omniverse's language, as it turns out,
is universal scene description.
And so that language is rather complex,
and so we've taught our Omniverse that language.
And so you can speak to it in English,
and it would directly generate USD.
And it would talk back in USD,
but converse back to you in English.
You could also look for information
in this world semantically.
Instead of the world being encoded semantically in language,
now it's encoded semantically in scenes.
And so you could ask it of certain objects
or certain conditions or certain scenarios,
and it can go and find that scenario for you.
It also can collaborate with you in generation.
You could design some things in 3D.
It could simulate some things in 3D,
or you could use AI to generate something in 3D.
Let's take a look at how this is all going to work.
We have a great partnership with Siemens.
Siemens is the world's largest industrial engineering
and operations platform.
You've seen now so many different companies
in the industrial space.
Heavy Industries is one of the greatest final frontiers of IT,
and we finally now have the necessary technology
to go and make a real impact.
Siemens is building the industrial metaverse,
and today we're announcing that Siemens is connecting
their crown jewel accelerator to NVIDIA Omniverse.
Let's take a look.
Siemens technology is transformed every day for everyone.
Team Center X, our leading product lifecycle management software
from the Siemens accelerator platform,
is used every day by our customers
to develop and deliver products at scale.
Now we are bringing the real and the digital worlds
even closer by integrating NVIDIA AI
and Omniverse technologies into Team Center X.
Omniverse APIs enable data interoperability
and physics-based rendering to industrial-scale design
and manufacturing projects.
Our customers, HD Hyundai,
market leader in sustainable ship manufacturing,
builds ammonia and hydrogen power chips,
often comprising over 7 million discrete parts.
With Omniverse APIs, Team Center X lets companies like HD Hyundai
unify and visualize these massive engineering data sets interactively
and integrate generative AI to generate 3D objects
or HDRI backgrounds to see their projects in context.
The result, an ultra-intuitive, photoreal,
physics-based digital twin that eliminates waste and errors,
delivering huge savings in cost and time.
And we are building this for collaboration,
whether across more Siemens accelerator tools like Siemens NX
or STAR CCM+, or across teams
working on their favorite devices in the same scene together.
And this is just the beginning.
Working with NVIDIA, we will bring accelerator computing,
generative AI and Omniverse integration
across the Siemens accelerator portfolio.
The professional voice actor
happens to be a good friend of mine, Roland Bush,
who happens to be the CEO of Siemens.
Once you get Omniverse connected into your workflow,
your ecosystem,
from the beginning of your life,
to engineering, to manufacturing planning,
all the way to digital twin operations,
once you connect everything together,
it's insane how much productivity you can get.
And it's just really, really wonderful.
All of a sudden, everybody's operating on the same ground truth.
You don't have to exchange data and convert data, make mistakes.
Everybody is working on the same ground truth.
From the beginning of your life,
everybody is working on the same ground truth.
From the design department to the art department,
the architecture department, all the way to the engineering
and even the marketing department.
Let's take a look at how Nissan has integrated Omniverse
into their workflow.
And it's all because it's connected by all these wonderful tools
and these developers that we're working with.
Take a look.
Let's take a look.
That was not an animation.
That was Omniverse.
Today, we're announcing that Omniverse Cloud
streams to the Vision Pro.
It is very, very strange
that you walk around virtual doors
when I was getting out of that car.
And everybody does it.
It is really, really quite amazing.
Vision Pro, connected to Omniverse,
portals you into Omniverse.
And because all of these CAD tools
and all these different design tools are now integrated
and connected to Omniverse,
you can have this type of workflow.
Really incredible.
Let's talk about robotics.
Everything that moves will be robotic.
There's no question about that.
It's safer, it's more convenient.
One of the largest industries is going to be automotive.
We build the robotic stack
from top to bottom, as I was mentioning,
from the computer system,
but in the case of self-driving cars,
including the self-driving application.
At the end of this year,
or I guess beginning of next year,
we will be shipping in Mercedes
and then shortly after that, JLR.
And so these autonomous robotic systems
are software defined.
They take a lot of work to do,
has computer vision,
intelligence, control and planning,
all kinds of very complicated technology
and takes years to refine.
We're building the entire stack.
However, we open up our entire stack
for all of the automotive industry.
This is just the way we work.
The way we work in every single industry,
we try to build as much of it as we can
so that we understand it,
but then we open it up so that everybody can access it.
Whether you would like to buy just our computer,
which is the world's only
functional, safe,
ASLD system
that can run AI,
this functional, safe,
ASLD quality computer
or the operating system on top
or, of course,
our data centers, which is in
basically every AV company in the world.
However you would like to enjoy it,
we're delighted by it.
Today we're announcing that BYD,
the world's largest EV company,
is adopting our next generation,
it's called Thor.
Thor is designed for transformer engines.
Thor, our next generation
AV computer, will be used
by BYD.
You probably don't know this fact that we have
over a million robotics developers.
We created Jetson,
this robotics computer.
We're so proud of it. The amount of software that goes on top of it
is insane. But the reason why we can do it at all
is because it's 100% CUDA compatible.
Everything that we do,
everything that we do in our company,
is in service of our developers.
And by us being able to maintain
this rich ecosystem
and make it compatible with everything that you
access from us,
we can bring all of that incredible capability
to this little tiny computer
we call Jetson, a robotics computer.
We also today are announcing
this incredibly advanced
new SDK. We call it
Isaac Perceptor.
Isaac Perceptor,
most of the robots today
are pre-programmed.
They're either following rails on the ground,
digital rails, or they'd be following
April tags. But in the future,
they're going to have perception. And the reason
why you want that is so that you could easily
program it. You say,
I would like to go from point A to point B
and it will figure out a way to navigate
its way there. So by
only programming waypoints,
the entire route could be
adaptive. The entire environment could
be reprogrammed, just as I showed you at the very beginning
with the warehouse.
You can't do that with
pre-programmed AGVs.
If those boxes fall down,
they just all gum up and they just wait there for somebody
to come clear it. And so now
with the Isaac Perceptor,
we have incredible
state-of-the-art vision odometry,
3D reconstruction,
and in addition to 3D reconstruction,
depth perception. The reason for that
is so that you can have two modalities
to keep an eye on what's happening in the world.
Isaac Perceptor.
The most used
robot today is
the manipulator,
manufacturing arms, and they are also
pre-programmed. The computer vision
algorithms, the AI algorithms,
the control and path planning algorithms
that are geometry aware,
incredibly computational and intensive.
We have made these
CUDA accelerated.
So we have the world's first CUDA accelerated
motion planner that is
geometry aware.
You put something in front of it, it comes up
with a new plan and articulates around it.
It has excellent
perception for pose estimation
of a 3D object.
Not just, not its pose in 2D,
but its pose in 3D. So it has to
imagine what's around and
how best to grab it.
So the foundation
pose, the grip foundation,
and the
articulation algorithms are now
available. We call it Isaac Manipulator.
And they also just
run on NVIDIA's computers.
We are
starting to do some really
great work in the next generation
of robotics. The next generation of
robotics will likely be
a humanoid robotics.
We now have the necessary technology
and as I was describing earlier,
the necessary technology
to imagine generalized
human robotics.
In a way, human robotics is
likely easier and the reason for that is
because we have a lot more
imitation training data
that we can provide the robots because we
are constructed in a very similar way.
It is very likely that the humanoid
robotics will be much more useful
in our world because we created the
world to be something that we can
interoperate in and work well in.
And the way that we set up our work
stations and manufacturing and logistics,
they were designed for humans.
They were designed for people. And so these
humanoid robotics will likely be much
more productive to deploy.
While we are creating
just like we are doing with the others,
the entire stack.
Starting from the top, a foundation
model that learns from
watching video, human
examples,
it could be in video form, it could be in
virtual reality form.
We then created a gym
for it called Isaac Reinforcement
Learning Gym, which allows
the humanoid robot to
learn how to adapt to the
physical world. And then an incredible
computer, the same computer
that's going to go into a robotic car,
this computer will run inside
a humanoid robot called Thor.
It's designed for transformer engines.
We've combined
several of these into one video.
This is something that you're going to really love.
Take a look.
We create
smarter
and faster.
We push it to fail
so it can learn.
We teach it
then help it teach itself.
We broaden its understanding
to take on new challenges
with absolute precision
and succeed.
We make it perceive
and move
and even reason
so it can share our world
with us.
Mmm.
This is where inspiration leads us.
The next frontier.
This is Nvidia Project Group.
A general purpose
foundation model
for humanoid robot learning.
The group model takes multimodal
instructions and past interactions
as input and produces
the next action for the robot to
execute.
We developed Isaac Lab,
a robot learning application
to train Group, on Omniverse
Isaac Sim.
And we scale out with Osmo,
a new compute orchestration service
that coordinates workflows across
DGX systems for training
and OVX systems for simulation.
With these tools, we can train Group
in physically based simulation
and transfer zero shock
to the real world.
The Group model will enable
a robot to learn from a handful
of human demonstrations
so it can help with everyday tasks.
And emulate human movement
just by observing us.
This is made possible
with Nvidia's technologies
that can understand humans from videos,
train models and simulation,
and ultimately deploy them
directly to physical robots.
Connecting Group to a large
language model even allows it
to generate motions by following
natural language instructions.
Hi, GR1.
Can you give me a high five?
You're big. Let's high five.
Can you give us some cool moves?
Sure. Check this out.
All this incredible intelligence is powered
by the new Jetson Thor Robotics chips
designed for Group,
built for the future.
With Isaac Lab, Osmo
and Group, we're providing the building blocks
for the next generation of
AI-powered robotics.
Music
Applause
About the same size.
The soul of Nvidia.
The intersection of computer graphics,
physics, artificial intelligence.
It all came to bear
at this moment.
The name of that project,
General Robotics 003.
I know. Super good.
Super good.
Well, I think we have
some special guests.
Do we?
Hey, guys.
So I understand you guys
are powered by Jetson.
They're powered by Jetson.
Little Jetson
robotics computers inside.
They learn to walk
in Isaac Sim.
Ladies and
gentlemen,
this is orange
and this is the famous
green. They are the
BDX robots
of Disney.
Amazing
Disney research.
Applause
Come on, you guys. Let's wrap up.
Let's go.
Five things.
Where are you going?
I sit right here.
Don't be afraid.
Come here, green. Hurry up.
What are you saying?
No, it's not time to eat.
I'll give you a snack in a moment.
Let me finish up real quick.
Come on, green. Hurry up.
Stop wasting
time.
Five things.
Five things. First,
a new industrial revolution.
Every data center should be
accelerated. A trillion dollars
worth of installed data centers
will become modernized over the next
several years. Second, because of the computational
capability we brought to bear, a new way
of doing software has emerged. Generative
AI, which is going to create
new infrastructure
dedicated to doing one thing
and one thing only. Not for
multi-user data centers, but
AI generators. These AI
generation will create
incredibly valuable software.
A new industrial
revolution. Second, the computer
of this revolution, the computer
of this generation, generative
AI, trillion parameters,
Blackwell.
Insane amounts of computers
and computing. Third,
I'm trying to concentrate.
Good job.
Third, new
computer, new computer
creates new types of software. New
type of software should be distributed in a new
way. So that it can, on the one
hand, be an endpoint in the cloud and easy
to use, but still allow you
to take it with you. Because it is
your intelligence. Your intelligence
should be packaged up in a way
that allows you to take it with you. We call
them NIMS. And third, these
NIMS are going to help you create
a new type of application for the future.
Not one that you wrote completely from
scratch, but you're going to integrate
them like teams.
Create these applications. We have
a fantastic capability
between NIMS, the AI
technology, the tools,
NIMO, and the infrastructure DGX
cloud in our AI
foundry to help you create proprietary applications
and proprietary chatbots. And then lastly,
everything that moves in the future
will be robotic. You're not going to be
the only one. And these robotic
systems, whether they are
humanoid, AMRs,
self-driving cars,
forklifts, manipulating arms,
they will all need one
thing. Giant stadiums, warehouses,
factories.
There can be factories that are robotic,
orchestrating factories, manufacturing
lines that are robotics, building cars
that are robotics. These
systems all need one thing.
They need a platform,
a digital platform,
a digital twin platform. And we call that
omniverse, the operating system
of the robotics world.
These are the five things that we
talked about today. What does NVIDIA
look like? What does NVIDIA look like
when we talk about GPUs?
There's a very different image that I have
when people ask me about GPUs.
First, I see a bunch of software
stacks and things like that. And second,
I see this. This is
what we announce to you today.
This is Blackwell. This is
the platform.
Amazing, amazing processors,
NVLink switches,
networking systems,
and the system design is a
miracle. This is Blackwell.
And this, to me, is what a GPU
looks like in my mind.
Thank you.
Listen, orange, green,
I think we have one more treat for everybody.
What do you think? Should we?
Okay, we have one more thing to show you.
Roll it.
Thank you, thank you, have a great, have a great GTC, thank you all for coming, thank
you.
Thank you, thank you, have a great, have a great GTC, thank you, have a great GTC, thank you.
Thank you, thank you, have a great, have a great GTC, thank you.
Thank you, thank you, have a great GTC, thank you.